Two months ago, my kids and I huddled around a cell phone
قبل شهرين، اجتمعت مع أطفالي حول الهاتف؛
watching the live stream of the Game Awards,
لنشاهد البث المباشر لجوائز الألعاب،
one of the video game industry's biggest nights.
أحد أهم الأحداث بالنسبة لصناعة ألعاب الفيديو.
They announced the nominees for the Game for Impact,
أعلنوا المرشحين لفئة الألعاب الأكثر تأثيرًا،
an award that's given to a thought-provoking video game
وهي جائزة تُمنح للعبة محفّزة للتفكير
with a profound prosocial message or meaning.
ولها معني اجتماعي عميق.
They opened the envelope
فتحوا الظّرف
and they read the title of our video game.
وأعلنوا اسم لعبتنا.
An award ...
جائزة ..
for impact.
للأكثر تأثيرًا!
It was almost funny, actually,
كان الأمر غريبًا؛
because I always thought that winning an award like that
لأنّني لطالما ظننت أن الفوز بجائزةٍ كهذه
would have this huge impact on my life,
سيترك تأثيرًا كبيرًا على حياتي،
but I found that the opposite is true.
لكنني اكتشفت أن العكس هو الصحيح.
The big nights,
الأحداث الهامة
the accomplishments --
والإنجازات
they fade.
تتلاشى.
But the hardest nights of my life have stuck with me,
بينما بقيت أصعب الليالي في حياتي معي،
impacting who I am
تؤثّر عليّ،
and what I do.
وعلى أفعالي.
In 2010, my third son, Joel, was diagnosed with a rare and aggressive brain tumor.
في عام 2010، تم تشخيص ابني الثالث "جويل" بورم دماغي نادر.
And before that year was finished,
وقبل نهاية العام،
doctors sat my husband and I down
جلسنا أنا وزوجي مع الأطباء
and let us know that his tumor had returned
وأخبرونا أن الورم تجدّد،
despite the most aggressive chemotherapy and radiation that they could offer him.
بالرغم من العلاج الكيماوي والإشعاعي المكثف.
On that terrible night,
في هذه الليلة المريعة،
after learning that Joel had perhaps four months to live,
وبعدما عرفت أن "جويل" سيعيش لأربعة أشهر تقريبًا،
I cuddled up with my two older sons in bed --
احتضنت طفليّ الأكبر سنًا في السرير،
they were five and three at the time --
كانوا خمسة وثلاثة في ذلك الوقت -
and I never really knew how much they understood,
وأنا لم أعرف حقا كم فهموا،
so I started telling them a bedtime story.
لذلك بدأت أقول لهم قصة قبل النوم.
I told them about this very brave knight named Joel
أخبرتهما عن فارس شجاع اسمه "جويل"
and his adventure fighting a terrible dragon called cancer.
وعن مغامراته ضد تنين مخيف اسمه سرطان.
Every night, I told them more of the story,
كل ليلة، قلت لهم أكثر من القصة،
but I never let the story end.
لكنّني لم أنهِ القصة أبدّا.
I was just building up a context that they could understand
كنت فقط أنشئ سياقًا يمكنهما فهمه
and hoping that our prayers would be answered
على أمل أن تتحقق دعواتنا،
and I would never have to tell them that that knight,
وألا اضطر أن أخبرهما أن هذا الفارس
who had fought so bravely,
الذي قاتل بشجاعة
was done fighting
قد استسلم،
and could rest now, forever.
وسينام للأبد.
Fortunately, I never did have to finish that bedtime story.
لحسن الحظ، لم اضطر لإنهاء القصة.
My children outgrew it.
أطفالي أضافوا إليها.
Joel responded better than anyone expected to palliative treatment,
استجاب "جويل" بشكل غير متوقّع للعلاج بالمسكنات،
and so instead of months,
وبدلًا من أشهر
we spent years learning how to love our dying child with all of our hearts.
أمضينا أعوامًا نتعلم كيف نحب طفلنا الذي يحتضر.
Learning to recognize that shameful feeling
نتعلم التعايش مع الشعور المخزي
of holding back just a little love
لكبح حبّنا قليلًا؛
to try to spare ourselves just a little pain
لنحمي أنفسنا من بعض الألم لاحقًا.
somewhere further down the road.
في مكان آخر أبعد من الطريق.
We pushed past that self-preservation
دفعنا جانبًا الحاجة للحفاظ على الذات
because Joel was worth loving even if that love could crush us.
لأن "جويل" استحق الحب حتى لو حطّمَنا ذاك الحب.
And that lesson of intense vulnerability has changed me ...
وهذه التجربة مع الضعف الشديد غيّرتني
more than any award ever could.
أكثر مما قد تفعله أي جائزة.
We started living like Joel could live,
بدأنا نعيش على أساس أن "جويل" قد يعيش،
and we began developing a video game called "That Dragon, Cancer."
وبدأنا نطوّر لعبة تسمّي (ذلك التنين سرطان - That Dragon, Cancer)
It was the story of Joel.
كانت قصة جويل.
It was the story of hope in the shadow of death.
كانت قصة أمل في ظل الموت.
It was the story of faith
كانت قصة عن الإيمان
and doubt,
والشك،
and the realization that a wrestle with doubt is a part of faith --
وإدراك أن معركتنا مع الشك هي جزء من الإيمان،
maybe the biggest part of it.
وربما الجزء الأكبر.
It was a story that began as a miracle
كانت قصة بدأت كمعجزة
and ended as a memorial.
وانتهت كتأبين.
(Music)
(موسيقي)
(Giggle)
(ضحك)
(Clapping)
(تصفيق)
(Music)
(موسيقي)
(Video) Dad: Bouncing around, do you like that?
(فيديو) الأب: تقفز، أتحب هذا؟
(Giggle)
(ضحك)
I love your giggle.
كم أحب ضحكتك!
(Music)
(موسيقي)
(Giggle)
(ضحك)
[A Journey of Hope In the Shadow of Death]
[رحلة أمل في ظل الموت]
[That Dragon, Cancer]
[ذلك التنين، سرطان]
(Music)
(موسيقى)
When you play "That Dragon, Cancer,"
عندما تلعب "ذلك التنين، سرطان"
you're transformed into a witness of Joel's life,
ستصبح شاهدًا على حياة "جويل"،
exploring an emotional landscape,
وتكتشف معالمها العاطفية،
clicking to discover more of what we as a family felt and experienced.
تلعب لتتعرّف أكثر على ما شعرنا به كعائلة.
It feels a little bit like analyzing interactive poetry
إنها تشبه قراءة الشعر التفاعلي إلى حد ما؛
because every game mechanic is a metaphor,
لأن كل عنصر في اللعبة له إسقاط،
and so the more the player asks themselves
وهكذا كلما كان اللاعب يسأل نفسه
what we as designers were trying to express and why,
عما نحاول كمصممين أن نعبر عنه ولماذا،
the richer the experience becomes.
كلما أصبحت تجربته أعمق.
We took that vulnerability that Joel taught us,
لقد استخدمنا الضعف الذي تعلمناه من "جويل" في تصميم اللعبة.
and we encoded the game with it.
وقمنا بترميز اللعبة به.
Players expect their video games to offer them branching narrative
يتوقع اللاعبون أن يكون للألعاب مسارات متشعبة؛
so that every decision that they make feels important
كي يشعروا بأهمية أي قرار يتخذونه؛
and can change the outcome of the game.
لأنه قد يغير نهاية اللعبة.
We subverted that principle of game design,
لكنّنا ألغينا هذا المبدأ،
collapsing the choices in on the player
وهدمنا الخيارات أمام اللاعبين؛
so that they discover for themselves
كي يكتشفوا بأنفسهم
that there is nothing that they can do that will change the outcome for Joel.
أنه ليس بوسعهم فعل شيء لتغيير ما سيحدث لـ"جويل".
And they feel that discovery as deeply and desperately as we felt it
وأن يتأثروا بذلك عميقًا كما تأثرنا به
on nights when we held Joel in our arms praying for hours,
طوال الليالي التي احتضنَا فيها "جويل" ونحن ندعو لساعات
stubbornly holding out hope for a grace that we could not create for ourselves.
متمسّكين بالأمل في أمنية لا يمكننا تحقيقها لأنفسنا.
We'd all prefer to win,
جميعنا نفضّل الفوز،
but when you discover that you can't win,
لكن عندما تدرك أنك لن تحقق الفوز،
what do you value instead?
فما الذي ستقدّره بدلًا عنه؟
I never planned to write video games,
لم أخطط أبدًا لكتابة ألعاب،
but these moments that really change our lives,
لكن اللحظات التي تغير حياتنا
they often come as the result of our hardship -- and not our glory.
عادةً ما تتسبّب فيها معاناتنا وليس نجاحنا.
When we thought that Joel could live,
عندما اعتقدنا أن "جويل" قد يعيش؛
I left the game designing to my husband.
تركت تصميم الألعاب لزوجي.
I chimed in here and there
شاركت أحيانًا
with a scene or two and some suggestions.
بمشهد أو اثنين وبعض الاقتراحات.
But after the night that Joel died,
لكن بعد الليلة التي توفّي فيها "جويل"،
the passion,
الشغف،
the possibility of sharing Joel's life through our video game --
وفرصة مشاركة حياة "جويل" من خلال لعبتنا
it was something that I couldn't resist.
كان أمراً لا يقاوَم.
I started writing more,
بدأت أكتب أكثر،
I sat in on our team's design meetings,
حضرت اجتماعات فريق التصميم،
I added more ideas and I helped direct scenes.
أضفت أفكارًا، وشاركت في إخراج المشاهد.
And I discovered that creating a video game is telling a story,
واكتشفت أن صنع لعبة فيديو يشبه رواية قصّة،
but with an entirely new vocabulary.
لكن باستخدام عناصر جديدة كليًا.
All the same elements of imagination and symbolism are there,
فجميع عناصر الخيال والرمزية موجودة،
but they're just partnered with player agency
لكنها تتداخل مع درجة تحكم اللاعب،
and system responsiveness.
وتجاوب النظام معه.
It's challenging work.
إنّه عمل صعب.
I have to think in a totally new way to do it,
ويجب أن أفكر بطريقة جديدة لأقوم به،
but I love it.
لكنّني أحبه.
And I wouldn't have known that without Joel.
وما كنت لأعرف ذلك لولا "جويل".
Maybe you're a little surprised
ربما أنت متفاجئ قليلّا
by our choice to share our story of terminal cancer through a video game.
لأننا اخترنا مشاركة قصتنا عن السرطان من خلال لعبة.
Perhaps you're even thinking like so many people before you:
وربما تفكر مثل الكثيرين وتقول
cancer is not a game.
أن السرطان ليس لعبة.
Well, tell that to any pediatric cancer parent
قل هذا لوالد طفل مصاب بالسرطان
that's ever taken an exam glove and blown it up into a balloon,
قام بنفخ قفاز طبّي كبالون،
or transformed a syringe into a rocket ship,
أو حوّل حقنة إلى صاروخ طائر،
or let their child ride their IV pole through the hospital halls
أو ترك طفله يقود حامل المحاليل في المشفى
like it was a race car.
كأنه سيارة سباق.
Because when you have children,
لأنك عندما تحظي بأطفال،
everything is a game.
كل شيء يكون لعبة.
And when your young child experiences something traumatic,
وعندما يتعرض طفلك لأمرٍ صادم،
you work even harder to make sure that their life feels like a game
فإنك تبذل ما في وسعك لتجعل حياته تبدو كلعبة؛
because children naturally explore their worlds through play.
لأن الأطفال يستكشفون عالمهم عن طريق اللعب.
While cancer can steal many things from a family,
إذا كان السرطان سيسرق الكثير من عائلة ما،
it shouldn't steal play.
فلا يجب أن يسرق اللعب.
If you're listening to me and you're trying to imagine this family
إذا كنت تستمع لي محاولًا تصوّر هذه العائلة
that revolves entirely around a dying child,
التي تتمحور حياتها كليًا حول طفل يحتضر،
and you can't imagine joy as part of that picture,
ولا يمكنك تخيّل السعادة كجزء من تلك الصورة،
then we were right to share our story with you,
فنحن إذن محقّون في مشاركة قصتنا معك؛
because that season of our life was hard.
لأن هذه الفترة من حياتنا كانت شاقة،
Unspeakably hard at times,
شاقة على نحو لا يوصف أحيانًا،
but it was also pure hope,
لكنها حملت أملًا نقيًا
deep love
وحبًا عميقًا
and joy like I have never experienced since.
وسعادة لم أشعر بها ثانيةً.
Our video game was our attempt to share that world
لعبتنا كانت محاولة لمشاركة هذا العالم
with people who hadn't experienced it before,
مع أشخاص لم يعيشوه من قبل؛
because we never could imagine that world until it became ours.
لأننا لم نكن لنتخيله إلا بعدما أصبح عالمنا.
We made a video game that's hard to play.
لقد صنعنا لعبة يصعُب لعبها.
It will never be a blockbuster.
لن تحقق نجاحًا ساحقًا.
People have to prepare themselves to invest emotionally
على الناس أن يستعدوا لاستثمار مشاعرهم
in a story that they know will break their hearts.
في قصةٍ يعرفون مسبقًا أنها ستحطم قلوبهم.
But when our hearts break,
لكن قلوبنا عندما تتحطم،
they heal a little differently.
فإنها تتعافى على نحو مختلف قليلًا.
My broken heart has been healing with a new and a deeper compassion --
قلبي يتعافى على نحو أكثر تعاطفًا،
a desire to sit with people in their pain,
ورغبةً في مرافقة الناس في حزنهم،
to hear their stories and try to help tell them
أنأاسمع قصصهم وأحاول المساعدة على نشرها؛
so that they know that they're seen.
حتى يشعروا بوجود من يراهم.
On the night when "That Dragon, Cancer" won the Game for Impact Award,
في ليلة فوز "ذلك التنين، سرطان" بجائزة اللعبة الأكثر تأثيراُ،
we cheered,
هتفنا فرحًا،
we smiled and we talked about Joel
ابتسمنا وتحدثنا عن "جويل"،
and the impact he had on our life --
وعن تأثيره في حياتنا
on all of those hard and hopeful nights that we shared with him
طوال الليالي الصعبة والمفعمة بالأمل التي أمضيناها معه
when he changed our hearts
حيث غيّر قلوبنا،
and taught us so much more about life and love and faith and purpose.
وعلّمنا الكثير عن الحياة والحب والإيمان والهدف الأسمى.
That award will never mean as much to me as even a single photograph of my son,
هذه الجائزة لن تمثّل بالنسبة لي ما قد تمثله صورة واحدة لابني،
but it does represent all of the people who his life has impacted,
لكنها تمثّل كل الأشخاص الذين أثّرت حياته عليهم،
people I'll never meet.
أشخاص لن أقابلهم أبدًا.
They write me emails sometimes.
يراسلونني أحيانًا.
They tell me that they miss Joel, even though they never met him.
يخبرونني أنهم يفتقدون "جويل"، رغم أنهم لم يقابلوه قط.
They describe the tears that they've shed for my son,
يصفون دموعهم التي ذرفوها لأجل ابني،
and it makes my burden of grief just a little bit lighter
وهذا يخفف من ثقل حزني قليلًا
knowing that it's shared with a 10-year-old
عندما أعرف أنني شاركته مع طفل في العاشرة
watching a YouTube playthrough,
يشاهد مراجعة لعبة على YouTube،
or a doctor playing on his airplane with a smartphone,
أو طبيب يلعب على هاتفه أثناء رحلة طيران،
or a professor introducing Joel to her first-year philosophy students.
أو أستاذه جامعية تقدّم "جويل" لطلابها في صف الفلسفة.
We made a video game that's hard to play.
لقد صنعنا لعبة يصعُب لعبها.
But that feels just right to me,
لكنني أشعر بالرضا التام؛
because the hardest moments of our lives
لأن أصعب لحظات حياتنا
change us more than any goal we could ever accomplish.
تُغيّرنا أكثر من أي هدف قد نحققه.
Tragedy has shifted my heart
المأساة غيّرت قلبي
more than any dream I could ever see come true.
أكثر من أي حلم قد أراه يتحقق.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)